so is the susima suitor
some mutant nicaya and Adonis on you too
suta number 70 so on that occasion this
is really the more probable so now I'm
not occasion many bhikkhus had in the
presence of the Buddha described onion
which is like seems to be the kind of
full knowledge or complete knowledge of
the our house
and is and it's defined as their so we
understand birth is destroyed the whole
life has been lived what should be done
has been done there's no more of this
so the Venerable system has heard is
that apparently lots of bhikkhus have
described this knowledge
in the presence of the Buddha
and then he approaches than sorry
venerable sister approaches these these
bhikkhus asks those bhikkhus is it
really true that in the presence of the
Buddha the complete knowledge has been
described the complete knowledge
full knowledge has been described by the
vanderwaal's we understand birth is
destroyed the whole life has been lived
what should be done has been done
there's no more of this yes friend
so then summer says okay then so knowing
in this way
seeing in this way do you Venables
experience various sorts of special
powers
you become one being one
morty walk through walls you return you
fly across legged through space no
friends
then knowing in this way seeing in this
way do you Venables dwell having
contacted with the body those peaceful
immaterial Liberation's that transcend
matter no friend
here novella says this answer than the
non-attainment of these being these
things friends how could this be
talking to me declaring the final
knowledge yeah without any of those
attendants yeah
we are liberated by understanding front pandava muta
we're liberated by the stunning print I
do not understand in detail the meaning
of what has been celebrated by these in
brief by these deep these venerable ones
it would be good if the Venables could
could speak the truth so that I might
understand in detail the meaning of what
has been said
you might understand friend susima they
say well you might not understand even
so for your liberated by understanding
that venerable system having got up from
his seat went to the Buddha and paid
respects sat down at one side and told
reported all that ripples at a lot
and the Buddha says this before another
system this is the sentence beforehand
Sumer
dammit ectomy on
is the pali word
can we read first the sentence
goodra Hollywood okay we'll say before
well okay so I'll help my translation is
beforehand to simmer
the knowledge of the endurance of things
afterwards the knowledge of Nirvana
now that the usual translations of fats
I've had a look at various different
some scholars party scholars have
translated it the knowledge of the
stability of darkness who's dumber deep
dammit Tipton Jana sonar now is like the
knowledge titties like standing or
persistence like the third 33rd is
theater there arisings manifest yes in
his many forces that existing world
changes many things that's what I've
think of it so that the normal
translations are the knowledge of the
stability of the dummer the knowledge of
the regularity of the dhamma the
knowledge of the steadfast of the dharma
the knowledge of the persistence of
principles the knowledge of the
stability of natural principles yeah
which is all it seem to be ok it's ok
but it's not as something they would be
so directly pertaining yeah to the
understanding and being in Ireland which
they will clearly answer that it should
pertain yeah I mean here's how these
people aren't without any of those
powers and able to say well this is
because they this is what they know and
if you take that to mean just the
steadfastness of the Dhamma many people
know that yeah
many people can't accept it maybe we
have faith in it many people are gonna
understand that to a great degree but
far from being anywhere nearly in
elephant
so then you could look for something
more concise which is I think what
you've done in the translation so
instead of dommatina instead of dama
meaning the dama dama means phenomenon
hmm so they know the the arising the
manifestation resistance they then
brings de Bona to development as in this
passion because if you understand the
nature of anything that has appeared the
result of that understanding is always
this passion cannot result in other
things even if you don't want to be
dispassionate if you're understanding
things for what they are how they
possessed how they have arisen in that
manner you will experience this passion
towards the things letting go and so on
so Nibbana will be their automatic
result so that's I think that's the
interesting think
think
so normally the that senses just a
minute like many examples in suit is exactly
like many examples in suit is exactly
that like it's not like the common
translations are not wrong but they're
clearly not accurate enough yeah
but they clearly don't reveal the the
precise emphases in certain things but
it's more like a generic Oh Dom is great
that was good and dummy steadfast okay
yes but how can knowledge of that result
in direct ownership yeah and then you do
is econ there's the one the example I
was talking before was the feeling
prayed to suffering yeah yeah yeah sure
no stop and think about that what does
it mean feel afraid to suffering means
being subject to like feeling like
you're being hunted but I need a new
hunter reason if you want us to become
prey I'm in this jungle
and I feel like I'm praying here and I
don't know by going from home why from
which direction so how would you then
feel how would you describe the feeling
of a prey Oh anxiety dread guilt how
everybody can it do something about it
I'm not doing anything about this and
all this thing and it's like that's the
existential situation that needs to
proceed the right type of search towards
freedom from suffering the right type of
practice and the enemy will just read
over it Oh pray for suffering yes how
many people actually allow themselves to
feel prey to some sort of prey to
existence prayed to elements pray to the
body prayed to sickness aging and death
not money even the ones that practice
the Dharma don't start on their basis
they allow it maybe to some degree but
not fully
sort of explore what this what this kind
of strange phrase means yeah so it's
interesting he says beforehand
Susumu dalmatic Damiano dark and um
matatini on there so the knowledge of
the endurance of things afterwards the
knowledge of Nirvana
the reason why well your translation is
probably more correct is because it also
ties in with other practices that we've
talked about and resulting in Bona like
the would have been passing it when he
discerned the Petit Jean bada as in the
principle and then he remained mindful
of the endurance of the ii5 okay
incentive whatever reason and then his
mind became completely purified and
liberated and and you realize that for
most people recognizing like these three
characteristic arising is manifest
ceasing as benefits persistable changing
is manifest it's it's like if you
understand that but you'll be on the
level of the sotapanna probably because
they're the today's contemporary wrong
views are so much rooted in that the
kind of the perception of time because
Judas perception of time the projection
of the external world self self review
outside of yourself and all that and all
of them would be uprooted if you were to
understand the phenomena has a reason
and has the nature to persist on its own
yeah they have nothing to do with you
you and your reactions and your mental
movements in regard to the reason
phenomena are secondary to the
phenomenon simultaneous but secondary so
that side the first so so this damnit it
in the island is like this
is recognizing that things have a risk
they've already arisen and they aren't
enduring means like knowledge pretty
much the full understanding of the
nature of an enduring phenomenon dama
yeah and if your full understanding of
that as I said this passion will be a
natural result it's it's interesting
that it's so it's different it's being
distinguished from the knowledge of
Nirvana yeah yeah we proceeded yeah
sorry something you would upon which the
dispassion which is what Nibbana is can
be developed yeah I mean basically you
can say that the knowledge of Nirvana
but in order for you to be in Habana you
have to stay with that knowledge the
fishermen of time until your whole
experience has became like a cool-down
dispassionate and then you are in a
bonnet so it's like said the first is
about the endurance of things and the
second is about the cessation of things
the cessation of things existence or
things the aim of that jarrah cessation
of their endurance this the
because like and the reason was
endurance in single singled out there is
because arising is a form of endurance
ceasing is a form of interior's
resistible changing is a format señoras
exactly yeah the witness says well the
first mistake when people come across
this is demonstrated it always says
arising is manifest ceasing is
manifested resisting or changing or
changing while standing depending on
translation is manifested the three
periods the three sorry the three Peters
Buster's in future but then this is
manifested in spirits but people will
always read that as arising is
manifested persisting while changing is
manifested ceasing is manifested yeah
it's it's assumed to be like this linear
basically just observance of a duration
of a thing but it isn't the Buddha
didn't say that I said arising and
ceasing and manifested and persisting
were changing his manifest why is that
because it's not linear and you notice
okay let's look at the arising what is
arising arising is basically increasing
in its presence of something or this is
arising and the Buddha doesn't say or
arising starts no he said arising is
manifest yeah yeah it's not like you see
the point when you find the money
what's manifested you see it as already
arising and then same ceasing is
manifested not ceasing has ceased and
there is the end point after which the
no ceasing is manifested which means
ceasing is another reason experienced
forever as in increasing in its presence
is arising decreasing in its presence is
ceasing but it's still there either way
some dead phenomena is persisting while
remain what changing or changing while
remaining the same because if I say I'm
having like a good mood like I become
aware my good mood is manifested and you
could see it either arising or either
ceasing it's not going to there's no
third option to it
so that manifestation of a good mood
that you just recognized you became
mindful of you could see it as oh it's
increasing in its presence it's lasting
to words so to speak can you know can
you know I don't see it as particularly
it and rahi seems to be just one that
they know that no that's the point
manifestation mean is there yeah and
that's what you refer to you said study
within that you could see it
it's either towards me or away from me
so to speak towards my point of view are
away from it and if you look at closer
you realize oh yeah it's it's kind of
there with the kind of prospect of being
given more of itself so it's arising
it's that that's what it means it's
increasing in its presence while it's
still the same mood let's be manifested
yeah so that's why I keep saying people
to be more practically if you want to
reflect on these principles you can't do
it
arising is manifest duration ceasing
okay next no you're not you're leaving
yourself out yeah
so the manifestation is ordered in the
manifestation of what of something
arising for you or something ceasing
away from you as in my good mood I can
feel it sort of fading basically fading
in fading out the phenomena always
directional and you can no fading in or
fading out on account of it being there
already and remaining the same thing
because there would be no fading in for
example no fading out if the thing
changes from the point A to the point B
to the point C no it remains the same
thing that's what you can say it's
increasing of the same if it's a
completely different thing there would
be a no connection of of arising or
ceasing for that matter so that's why we
have arising and ceasing that a
manifested our on one level I the way
the nature is to persist one change and
recognizing that nature if you recognize
the nature of enduring resisting while
changing or changing what when in the
same you're already recognizing
discerning arising and ceasing I think
which is what the Buddha said he
discerned but for Buddha we pass he
discerned arising or ceasing of the five
aggregates and said that he discerned
their endurance this is one damage
that kind of knowledge has included
everything else within it so if you
develop the knowledge of enduring
phenomena me means you develop the
knowledge of non interfering with
gratuitous assumptions with this
phenomenon which also that means you
develop the knowledge of impossibility
to own this phenomena and then there is
no sense of ownership maintained in
regard to phenomena there is no sense of
self that's maintained as a result of
that ownership so Nibbana is the natural
product of that kind of understanding so
any other viruses at one point that
seeing the three characteristics isn't
isn't necessarily seeing a Nietzsche
doesn't doesn't
just isn't only seeing Annie chair so
venerable jnana Veera says the talking
about these three son Curtis our son
Telemachus so the characteristics is
your 10 min characteristics health yes
the characteristics of the determinant
yeah so what it is altering yes is the
you are basically manifested on your own
within a manifestation you discern
either it's increasing in its presence
of the same manifestation or is
decreasing in this present of the say
manifestation remain in the same
manifestation then it's another
manifestation that's either increasing
or decreasing there's no linear
increasing immediately leads to
decreasing the list when you think no
that's a completely external assumption
of how the world is for you but from
your point of view all you have is
feeling intention perceptions they're
they're enduring sometimes enduring more
toward you something enduring away from
you but the only the only reason you can
the world or a way or increasing or
decreasing can be intelligible is
because the same thing remains
yeah something and that's why / - Gela
it's probably the hardest thing for him
to understand is that allowing phenomena
to endure on its own so you can have the
same feeling for five days the same mood
and it's still the same mood otherwise
you wouldn't have a memory of it you
couldn't remember it that you've been
feeling like this for a number of days
but is this completely kind of
fabricated assumption of the external
world as the true objective all that I
can access with my subjectivity
objectively which is order the
contradiction in terms
and then all I have to do is observe
that world and that's how I improve my
sense of self failing to see that you're
always remained within your sense of
self whether you want it or not so when
you think about a public world that
world is part of your experience and
assumptions on public which means your
thinking is a contradiction in terms
and that's what leads people to doing
this is like observational methodical
meditation techniques and practices
where right I'm feeling this I'm feeling
this I'm feeling this on I'm feeling
this appeal completely unaware of a
feeling and during on its own you don't
have to be attending to it in your stare
whether you want it or not and same goes
for the final grades that's what we said
oopah Don is not in the final grade it
cannot be in the not be part of
the structure of your experience if
desire lust from views in regards to the
structural experience in regard to the
five aggregates kupatana is there it's
almost like people doing these practices
are trying to make something endure yeah
yeah as if it's up to you as if it's a
yes and that's how their mindfulness is
not really mindfulness it's something
you could mindful is done properly it's
effortless that's very kind of too much
of it as the Buddha said himself it is
effortless because it's based on
discerning the enduring presence of the
body of the feelings of the thoughts and
the mud and you're on their own and you
can have me see that by just starting to
you the Durance is just something it's
already done by recognizing with
endurance is you get skilled in
discerning all three characteristics
that's what good assets among skilled in
discerning arising some monks are
skilled in discerning see singsong so
this is skilled in discerning like
enduring or all but the point is if you
discerning arising correctly you're
already discerning in Europe if you're
discerning ceasing correctly you're
already disowned enduring if you
discerning enduring correctly you're
already discerning all of it correctly
so either of those things can serve as a
basis for full understanding of that
principle that leads to dispassion so
that put us the interesting thing so
these three characteristics concisely in
decay the fundamental structure in virtue of
the fundamental structure in virtue of
which things are things virtue of which
that it is that that is to say things
are distinct one from another it is also
in virtue of this structure that all
experience including our hands is
intentional or teleological hmm the arts
experience is teleological houses the
petunias but with the arahat things no
longer have the particular significant
mining mine yeah so there's a few
recognized endurance of a reason
phenomena to the full extent as I said
you will be unable to maintain your
sense of ownership of it because you
realize it's completely independent it's
completely emotionally indifferent to
you as in it doesn't even know you exist
you your center self is redundant to it
but it's like it's a fundamental
structure that applies to both the
petition on the other hand well no it's
the Fargate that's a fundamental
structure is yeah there's no hidden
structure underneath that because that's
all you have and that's why I'm saying
the only difference then between
somebody who fully understood that and
someone has in his passion in this
passion which is protrusion an arrogant
ya Nibbana is nothing other than
dispassion in regard to the five
hundreds so cooling down a removal of
lust the fires are full greed in a
version is on the point I want to make
here is that Pendlebury goes on to say
the question of impermanence is not
simply that of establishing these three
characteristics well not simply exception courtesy in a
well not simply exception courtesy in a
sense of what Regina does like Luke
lasting and disappearing
that's what impermanence is okay so
you'd say that seeing there's three
characteristics in the right way yeah
that's why I show each other cuz on each
a is that impossibility to own the thing
it's not like look thing has disappeared
that's why it's impermanent that doesn't
make sense because disappearance is
manifested yet you're looking at the
content of what has disappeared or
rather changes its its appearance pretty
much and then claim that to be some
fundamental Anita how can you then do
that for your 500 you will need to
destroy your five agreements kill them
off in order to see them as impermanent
which means then all you need to do is
die to become another hunt but that's
not the case isn't it if I'm angry its
are not affected by death
hence the rebirth and the perpetuation
of samsara and if you remember your
previous lives you remember the five
minutes they do remain and when you say
also the family let's move from this
life to the next life no this life and
the next life are already within the
five aggregates so nothing moves just
the content of it changes for all of
those who wonder how deep as possible
it's just this it's interesting you
teachers seems to be saying that the
question of impermanence is not simply
that of establishing these three
characteristics is almost like these
three characteristics that things endure
and the knowledge of the endurance of
the endurance of that knowledge which is
also a thing and well in a way then in
itself i you could argue it's not enough
as and you need might be more
instruction to know how to regard things
is not mine yeah it's like even that can
be taken away there's no good reason why
that yeah sure man just be still
shake so this sort of thing like well
I'm pretty certain that all those
teachers with the wrong views in the
suitors are actually quite right from
the point of view of moderns wrong view
more than wrong view right so when when
the teacher was teaching the basis of
neither perception nor perception yeah
it's a lot aren't you but how will you
arrive there without being fully aware
of enduring phenomenon of mind different
extents of the mind they did you which
means you can be fully fully skilled in
discerning these things but it's it's
that passion dispassion side yeah you
need to you need to understand so if you
understand these things rightly as in
how the Buddha taught in a sense of
because of this it can't be mined and
started kind of applying it back onto
yourself in terms of not entertaining
the regulative sense of ownership that
will result in this passion obviously
that's a good implies with proper
understanding of enduring phenomenon
proper understanding of Dhamma I think
in the Vera talks about it in like a
structural sense which is also accurate
but in itself does not necessarily mean
you will be regarded as not mine but is
the Buddhist also making this
distinction between the knowledge of the
endurance of things these three
characteristics or the third
characteristic which yeah the knowledge
that no it's not a distinction he's
making distinction there is a
distinction between when universes
outlining these three characteristics
and when the Buddha says knowledge of
the three
okay hi okay I salute you make yang say
he'd be saying so the said before hand
there's the knowledge of the endurance
of things afterwards there's the
knowledge of Nirvana yes if you'll
become familiar with this passion did
you now fully understand but is that not
also like so the knowledge of Nirvana
means not means knowledge of the
possibility of the cessation of even
things enduring anything yeah all right
and that's that all enjoyed knowledge
already starts with knowledge of the
things yes yeah if properly understood
as would have a positive he got the
knowledge of principle petites on father
as in determined by something that
cannot be mind
and then he remained basically
contemplating the five aggregates
against the bed rebec drop of that
insight and he became another hand it's
just watching this temporal thing going
on hey it makes me think if there's the
well it's not temporal neither of those
knowledge isn't every hour I mean it's
only that you need to yeah it takes time
for all the passion to sort of dissipate
from all sorts of aspects that you've
been cultivating for lifetime yeah and
so in that sense you takes time but it's
basically persistence of the same right
view which is timeless because of that
it persists throughout this time it's
not it doesn't change through it through
that time so you see it as well I think
it's the same thing so I so the
I think it somewhere in me
he's in the you Donna where the
it is the Dharma where the Buddha says
in the after his enlightenment when he
first became a Buddha he's sitting under
the Bodhi tree nor Gaia in the first
watch of the night he contemplated at
each asana Prada
a Madonna with the green
yeah so he
we are contemplated
when is this this is when this arises
this arises
and
and then in this middle watch of the
night contemplated
I thought a party line and by the way
even that petition bar arises it's this
manifestation that's a reason so it's
more correct to say when this is present
this is present because people have been
misunderstanding but it's a mother for
so long so now when you say when this
arises this arises then this arises and
this sort of yes sorry yeah yeah when
does this when this this is so when
there is fading in off a phenomena
endurance is there did I say arises yeah
I mean yes so these they're fading in
Israel or failing artists there for as
long as there's this is this yeah for as
long as this has has a really massive
putter when this arises yeah this is run
simultaneously as if this and then in
the middle watch of the night the next
watch of the night he comes in place the
cessation with the cessation of this
when this isn't this isn't yeah it is
quite again it's fine just to this type
you got this temporal he does this one
first and then does this one second and
I'm wondering if actually the knowledge
of the endurance of things but the only
but the only reason the only reason you
can approach things temporarily as in
one two is because as a unit they're
already they're enduring yeah they give
you the duration that then you can take
it put it back take it put it back
but people confuse that as coming before
the duration it doesn't the whole is a
reason first yeah on a carnival you get
the part
yeah yes very sign a fatality yeah
I guess don't it's like college yes a my
dear Asuma
but there's a horde so the Buddhist holy
lady hope determines was apart and
that's why everybody's so bada is not a
collection of tough factors it's
basically exposition of the first factor
with this this is everybody's of other
starts this is what bitty super is okay
what with what what and then he goes
into scrubs and in different manner on
different occasions for people you know
that bit and then you just sort of try
to collect all this twelve factor
sixteen factors eight factors and then
induce some sort of duration explanatory
principle well it starts with the
principle again now so you begin with
the whole which is M as this is this and
then you'll be able to discern these
different manifestation of this this is
manifested that's it with manifestation
of what what is manifested and then you
go to this end but even that was kind of
only within like some Assam Buddhist
purview many atoms will not necessarily
see that previous Buddha did not see the
potato palette to the same detailed
extent and that's why we'll ago tone was
the foremost in expounding the Dhamma
because she could see in like absolutely
the every single facet but the previous
they would have a passive and he
understood but it's a bother he
basically described it as Oh nama Rupa
determines manana vijnana at the time is
nama Rupa like the two sticks holding
each other simultaneously that's it
that's what his formulation ended then
he contemplated manifestation of
increasing of the faregates
manifestation of decreasing of the five
aggregates as in contemplating enduring
of the areas in fiber grades and he
became an honor
so could could we say that so beforehand
so similar the knowledge of the
endurance of things afterwards the
knowledge of Nevada is that the same
thing as saying beforehand yeah like I
believe Parsi understood I thought he
just saw my father before he became the
Buddha petit okay
I was thinking petit Osama pod are an
aroma so the things in door think they
do the fact that they a llama in party
llama basically comes with passion and
this passion
principle needs to be understood whether
there is unknown or adenomas but once
you fully foulon this to the principal
you will know how passion results in all
these things within the same principle
and how this passion results in absence
of those things within the same
principle it's basically like sotapanna
is getting the right view of the
principle the sign of his mind
yeah okay so that's way before he is in
Habana so knowledge of the endurance of
things is simply the right view pretty
much on the level of the review yeah
possible for the knowledge of nevada now
the more effort you invest in the
knowledge of endurance the knowledge of
the damage the phenomena more dispassion
you will be developing but even if like
something's happened in the suitors the
artists erika noble disciple sotapanna
higher if they don't even necessarily
made the effort to clarify it all they
need to do is just basically not do
anything against the principle of
endurance and they will experience will
result in this passion in our hand ship
within the seven lifetimes at most and
anything against it is anything
basically based on that contradiction of
ignoring the fact that the news on its
own taking the ownership which contradicts
taking the ownership which contradicts
it and then acting a loss diversion and
distraction
so fully basically fully understanding
the right view means you experience
complete dispassion in regards to the
right view the endurance so that's what
were the first that the knowledge of the
endurance mmm then brings the knowledge
of mallanna yeah that knowledge of the
knowledge of the endurance the things
basically involves knowing that these
things are enduring of their own accord
for as long as they that's what
impermanence is as we discussed the
other day literally Nietzsche means dear
ones own nithya the sanskrit i'm
Nietzsche's then not one's own not dear
to me opposite of that so it's basically
how do you say unhone about turnable
yeah the characteristic of reach is kind
of characteristic of being an honorable
impossible to own because of that it's
not pleasant isn't it because of that
you cannot be your own sense of self
although you're not your own said you
think your own own things are yeah
unknown about inaccessible to you yeah
inaccessible to your will to your sense
of control to your master don't suppose
you need to ignore the fact that
fundamentally they're there on their own
yeah and that's how you maintain the
sense of ownership in regard to it which
can never truly enter those things and
become their owner